the quantity x squared plus b times x
can be represented geometrically using
an X by x square as pictured here and a
b by X rectangle placed underneath then
x squared plus BX represents this area
but we can take that b by X rectangle
and cut it into two equal pieces so that
one rectangle is a b over 2 by X
rectangle and the other one is a b over
2 by X rectangle but we can place one of
them on the right side of the square
like this now the area represented is
almost an X plus b over 2 by X plus b
over 2 square the only thing missing is
this lower right square that has
Dimensions B over 2 by B over two so the
area we're interested in is X plus b
over 2 squared minus B over 2 squared
this process is known as completing the
square